Miquel Barba

Software Engineer

Email: miquel.barba@gmail.com Linkedin: linkedin.com/in/miquelbarba/ Github: https://github.com/miguelbarba

Polyglot software engineer with more than 20 years of experience developing large-scale software systems, using a variety of languages and technologies. I have also held executive responsibilities as CTO, building & leading a team of more than 60 software engineers.

I care about software, I try to make software that is helpful for end users and easy to maintain. I follow good engineering practices such as test-driven development, continuous integration, code reviews, linters, SOLID & DRY principles.

RELEVANT SKILLS

Ruby & Ruby on Rails | Javascript & React & Cypress | Go & Gin & Gorm | React Native | Java & J2EE | Elixir | Python | Amazon Web Services | Docker | Mysql | Postgres | Redis | ElasticSearch | Git | Continuous integration | Continuous deployment | Agile methodologies | Startups & entrepreneurship | People management

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Instant API / Barcelona, Spain

Developer & Founder

Oct 2021

- Serverless platform to build APIs
- Ruby on Rails, Postgres, AWS, Docker, ES6, React

Rakuten TV / Barcelona, Spain

CTO

May 2017-Oct 2021

- Rakuten TV is the European leader in VOD & AVOD with the Rakuten App in millions of TVs and devices
- Managing a team of 60 developers (backend, playback, TV devices, mobile, web, QA)
- Establish a culture in the development team: KPIs & objectives, Ownership & Technical debt, Shared knowledge & Code review, Automation test & Continuous integration, Scrum
- Work with stakeholders (Product team & CEO): Roadmap definition. Estimations & risk assessment, **Deadlines**
- People management: recruiting, team building, performance review, increases & firing, conflict resolution.

Rakuten TV / Barcelona, Spain

Backend Team Manager

May 2011-May 2017

- Develop the core API of Rakuten TV that processes billions of requests monthly, supporting millions of TVs in 27 European markets.
- Ruby on Rails, Sidekiq, AWS, MySQL, ElasticSearch, Redis, Varnish, Docker
- Managing a team of 15 RoRs developers

Mobiquus / Barcelona, Spain

CTO & Co-Founder

Sep 2007-May 2011

- Mobiquus is a real time email push service that works in more than 200 devices, from low end mobiles to smartphones and offers advanced features such as voicemail, preview Office documents, images, videos, audio.
- My responsibilities include the entire product creation cycle: definition of functionalities, design of the technical architecture, development and testing.

INPS (In Practice Systems Ltd) / London, UK

Software Engineer - Java/J2EE developer

Dec 2006-Sep 2007

Tempos 21 / Barcelona, Spain

Software Architect

Sep 2002-Nov 2006

- Tempos21 is a joint venture created by Telefónica Móviles, Ericsson and HP to create and develop advanced mobile services. Tempos21 acts as a Application Service Provider providing messaging services (SMS, EMS, Wap-Push, MMS), location based services and projects.
- Java/J2EE, Oracle, SMS, Wap-Push, location based services

Gedas (contractor) / Barcelona, Spain

Software Engineer - Java/J2EE, Oracle Mar 2002-Sep 2002

GFT (contractor) / Barcelona, Spain

Software Engineer - Java/J2EE, Oracle Dec 2000-Mar 2002

Sopra Steria / Barcelona, Spain

Software Engineer - Java/J2EE Feb 2000-Dec 2000

Grupo En Efecto / Barcelona, Spain

Developer Jan 1999–Feb 2000

Sage Spain / Barcelona, Spain

Intern Feb 1998-Sep 1998

EDUCATION

Facultat d'Informàtica de Barcelona / Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya

Barcelona Jun 1999

Engineer, Computer Science